Nikhil Kumar

Address: Supriya Cinema Road, Behind Maruti Maker, Bettiah (Bihar)

Contact: +91-9472985849, +91-8709391763, E-mail ID: nikhilinst@gmail.com

Instrumentation engineer, Erection, Commissioning, Maintenance, trouble shooting of Cement Industry

Professional Summary:

Working as an Sr.Engineer (Instrumentation) at **LAXYO ENERGY Ltd.** Since 2020 in Operation & Maintenance Division of Services and project management. Have an Experience of Total 10+ years in the field of Erection, testing, commissioning and maintenance of all Instrumentation systems.

Company profile: Laxyo Energy Limited is an ISO 9001:2015 and ISO 18001:2007 OHSAS certified company. Its core business fields are in giving administrations to Turnkey construction of Railway Track, Maintenance of railway Track, Operation & Maintenance of plants including Cement, power, steel and Chemical plants, Roads and Civil construction work, Mechanized cleaning and house keeping and in Mining activites.

• Work Experience:

Organization: Laxyo Energy Ltd. **Duration:** Dec 2020 – Till Date

Designation: Sr. Instrument Engineer

Location: JUD Cement Ltd, Jaintia Hills (Meghalaya)

Organization: Siemens Ltd.

Duration: Aug 2017 – Nov 2020

Designation: Instrument Engineer

Location: Emami Cement Ltd, Panagarh (West Bengal)

Organization: JAGDAMBA CEMENT (P) LTD., NEPAL

Duration: Feb 2017 – July 2017

Designation: E&I Engineer

Location: Nepal

Organization: SHIVAM CEMENT (P) LTD., NEPAL

Duration: Nov. 2011 – Jan 2017 **Designation:** Junior Engineer (E&I)

Location: Nepal

Organization: JAYPEE GUJARAT CEMENT PLANT (JAYPEEGROUP)

Duration: Jan. 2009 - Sep. 2011

Designation: Junior Technician (Instrument)

Location: Kutchh (Gujarat)

Professional Qualification:

- ITI in Instrument mechanic from Shri M. GOPALRAO ITI (J.P. NAGAR REWA) M.P.
- Diploma in Electronics and Telecommunication from J.R.N Rajasthan Vidyapeeth.

Erection & commissioning engineer-:Erection and commissioning of heavy equipment's as Wagon Tippler, Gyratory Crusher, Stacker Reclaimer, Peddle Feeder, Lime stone handling plants, Coal handling plants and VRM with Packing Plant.

- Erection & Commissioning of complete Coal Handling Plant, Lime Stone Handling Plant, ESP, Wagon tippler, Pedal Feeder system including VFD & Field equipment's Root cause analysis for improving Invoice Quality through case and process management's.
- Commissioning, loop checking & fault diagnosis of field instruments, continuity test of field instruments with hand held terminal etc.
- VFD panels testing & commissioning of Siemens (S & G Series) and ABB.
- Supervision of Installation of field instruments, cables laying and cable termination of instruments.
- Installation, Calibration & Troubleshooting of all types of Transmitters, Switches, Load Cell, Actuators.
- Project Management functions involving resource planning, design & development and co-ordination with internal departments and equipment/system suppliers.
- · Communication with Head office & client regarding material and design issues update progress at site
- Responsible for initiating, planning, execution, monitoring, controlling and completing the project as scheduled and troubleshooting the problems while start up's, running and shutdown.
- Handling customer relation operations and developing customized solutions to meet client's specific requirements
- Maintenance of cooler & Kiln Camera.
- Maintenance & periodical calibration of field weigh feeder, Roto Packer Spouts, Pressure Transmitter, Pressure Switch, control Gates.
- Knowledge of calibration of Level Switch and Level Transmitter (LR-460 SIMENS & LR-560 SIEMENS)
- Knowledge of Weigh feeders (Make-SHENCK, FLSMidth Pfister)
- Involve in routine, shut-down & preventive maintenance and all trouble shooting in Pyro Section, grinding unit with packing plant.
- Knowledge about Troubleshooting in PLC schemes of DCS System (ABB & SIEMENS).
- Knowledge of Temperature sensor (RTD, Thermocouple, Pyrometer).
- Knowledge of Pressure Transmitter and Temperature transmitter, Sequential Timer.

- Wiring of MCC & I/O panel, LPBS, PCS, ZSS, BDS, damper Actuator (AUMA) and others.
- Knowledge of Bag filter, Solenoid valve, Control valve.
- Erection, Commissioning & shutdown Maintenance of field instruments like proximity, level sensors, temperature & pressure transmitters, actuator etc.
- Maintenance of cooler & Kiln Camera.
- Management of shift maintenance engineers, writing reports & related documentation.
- Knowledge of Rota packer (EEL &FLSMIDTH VENTOMATIC).
- Job allocation in daily planning jobs.
- Check compliance to major PMR's (Preventive Maintenance Routines).
- Make major maintenance plans for safe and timely maintenance of equipment.
- Maintain Log sheet and other document record as per ISO requirement.
- Check on ON-Going jobs for quality work.
- Co-ordinate with walk-by inspectors, planning, jobs in department daily/weekly jobs.

Educational Qualifications:

Qualification	Collage	Board/University	Year
10+2	Government Inter Collage	MP Board Bhopal	2008
10 th	Government High School	Bihar Board Patna	2005

Key Skills:

- Client Handling / Planning / Forecasting
- Service Management / Problem Management
- Knowledge/Training management
- Knowledge of Rates Sheet / Make Offer / Tender Process

• Strength:

- Strong analytical and problem solving skills
- Team player with ability to function in a multi-disciplinary environment
- Self-motivated, able to prioritize and plan effectively

Personal Profile:

Name : Nikhil Kumar

Father's Name : Shri Binod Kumar Singh

Date of birth : 02-Dec-1990

Nationality : Indian
 Sex : Male
 Marital Status : Married
 Language known : English, Hindi
 Current CTC : 4.80 LAC

• Expected CTC : As per Company Structural

Declaration:

I hereby declare that the information furnished above is true to the best of my knowledge.

Date: (Nikhil Kumar)

Place: